all right greetings everyone thanks for
joining it is
August 15th and we're in our final
discussion recorded discussion for
cohort three
next week we'll have uh kind of
unrecorded
discussion also this will be the day of
the Symposium so very auspicious day to
have
been concluded upon but today we're
going to talk about 10 and probably
anything else
so
Ali and Neil want to leave with anything
or and or we can go to ask Mel's
question first
well I've
quickly put in the last three questions
but we can I think we can get through
those so you know we can start with a
smiles
all right I'll just read it um and then
I happen to hear anyone's thoughts or or
more details now since I believe in
Occam's razor I denied the meaning of
awareness my suggestion is accessible
cognition and inaccessible cognition
it looks like we have an operating
system and implicit memory that's not
available
such as the procedural memory and
emotional memory I have some doubts
about the rest of the words like
Consciousness and awareness
and this is about the question the
opening quotation
of the chapter
beginning at the end in general we are
at least aware of what our minds do best
Neil or Ali
but
she's on my my last question which was
what is sentient about
active inference uh that's
it's put in the chapter title uh what
I've suggested as a teaser the chapters
really just summarizing
uh
it's
it doesn't
really say anything about Consciousness
I don't think
and what Carl is
it all seems to be getting more involved
in
discussions of Consciousness but I think
he always
maintains a distance between that and
works with with
people who are concerned with that but
it's it's more something where
active inference is is a framework for
um
well to help people who are looking at
sentence and consciousness
uh but doesn't really say anything
specifically about it
and so it seems to me
awesome
Ollie wanted anything on that
well yeah as far as I know sentience
um inactive inference literature is used
uh in rather technical sense in which
um sentient beings are just
[Music]
they're the beings that are responsive
uh to the external stimuli so that's
as simple as it gets uh and uh because
of its Simplicity it
uh
encompasses a whole array of things as
being sentient and uh it's not
necessarily uh restricted to biological
sentience or uh I don't know uh any
thing akin to
to the level of human intelligence or
human sentience and so on so it can
basically be applied to include
artificial sentience and everything even
uh virtual sentience such as I don't
know kind of thing that's just been
implemented algorithmically the software
and stuff so I get as it it was a
subject of the rather heated debate a
few months ago uh I mean the meaning of
the sentience is used in active
influence literature but
in all honesty it's not a novel use
either because uh this the same very
definition of a sentence that's used in
active inference is almost exactly the
same as one of the definitions
from Oxford English dictionaries so uh
it's not as controversial as it seems
but about the other terms such as
awareness and Consciousness well uh I
don't believe we have any sort of
consensus around those words yet in
active inference literature although in
recent papers around mum or Mom model of
active inference
um Maxwell and others are trying to
converge a consensus
on the word on the notion of
Consciousness in terms of active
inference
yeah what grade topics and also how cool
with chapter 10
published about a year and a half ago
maybe written in the previous months
leading up to one and a half years ago
how how there's certain similarities and
continuations of the discussion
um
yeah
Neil I really like the
um
the point about having us talk how how
active inference how it stays it's
unopiniated to the extent that it's
composable as a describing system
those properties are kind of like convex
concave
and there's a lot to say probably about
why certain expectations are around
certain kinds of X of accounts
scientific accounts
or just certain kinds of rhetorical
accounts like why that why some are
some way and some are not that's that's
this active influence of social sciences
um but that's the whole thing
having the descriptive framework
cartography compositional cognitive
cartography as per
the category Theory work and and that
whole area especially coming into play
and the mechanics and the Dynamics
it's like
Newtonian mechanics whatever you say
about it within the system it doesn't
have a preference for something moving
left or right or
up or down or something like that
that's just a bizarre
feature to bake into a measurement
framework
so when we look at active really is
presented in this textbook
whether as a behavioral researcher like
the figure 9.2 metabasian
so whether we approach it from this kind
of like classical behavioral researcher
or just researchers
perspective
or we approach it from the constructive
perspective with uh chapter six and all
of that
from six or from nine
uh science and engineering
eventually
maybe it'll come to be seen as an
account of the cartography
so hence that that Divergence with how
the the book lands of course this isn't
apologetics it's not to say that there's
like a perfect text or anything like
that
but I think that's kind of the area I
know that's a bunch of random thoughts
but it's chapter 10 these are the funny
things about the book that we only
really
come into relation with when we really
stay in the game and and compare how it
actually was
so we can look at some specific parts of
with the kinds of perspectives that that
people
mobilize today based upon like for
example only in the last few days
um
different experimental studies
I'll bring in one link just as an
example uh of course only only in for
educational use
this LinkedIn post
friston's AI law is proven fep explains
how neurons learned
anonymized to protect the innocent
um Kristen's
or everyone's slash no ones
AI
law
proven
is
explains how
what and if you think about this in
light of of how we've been thinking
about 10 then and now
how does this new artifact
from
today seem to you
yes Ali
well actually I haven't read the article
in its entirety but uh from what I've
seen uh
it's not fundamentally different from
the previous work done in establishing a
kind of empirical basis for active
inference but I'm not sure why it gained
so much attention now because uh to my
mind it's just a continuation of the
previous work done by the same group of
authors and establishing these kinds of
empirical bases for active inference but
uh
I can understand that it can seem as a
kind of culmination of this trajectory
of this line of research but uh I'm I'm
not sure if there's something
fundamentally new or I don't know
unprecedented explored in this recent
paper
or it's uh it's a kind of
um I mean as I said a culmination of all
the previous efforts done uh in this
area but on the other hand uh of course
because it's published in nature uh it
would attract lots of media attention
and
as we we've seen in the past few days on
Twitter or I don't know X or anything uh
it's the kind of uh you know
I I I'm not saying it's kind of
um uh it's reached the level of
hyperbole or something but uh
again I'm not sure if it's quite
beneficiary for active inference
literature if these kinds of
I mean this kind of news gets out of
proportion and delivers I mean it it
wouldn't be able to deliver as much as
it promises uh so
as a case in point that Denise holds uh
image here
seems to me a little bit out of
proportion
I don't know what you think but
um
maybe it's just my personal opinion that
it's always better to be uh
to to keep some restraint about these
things and that let let everything loose
and
because
it has it can have dire consequences for
any future research if uh it it it
doesn't get what it promises or it
doesn't deliver what it promises or
something like that so
that's just my personal opinion on that
excellent I'll leave
very measured very diplomatic
Neil
yeah I'm I'm only just looking at the
article now
[Music]
yeah I don't think that
I'll just bring in one other
um cultural artifact that that like uh
back in the game I just remember being
like
again everything everyone's Bay is
optimal so it's it's I I'm not saying I
would have done anything differently I'm
not saying anything like that I just
want to point to these um historical
um image Meme and and everything
this was the year that the Alias
interview with Martin forger and Carl
had been
um well all you need is the title
but what else a funny thing I just
thought okay I know that it's the
article is not ever defined by the
headline Etc
genius neuroscientist
so okay speculative but singular
and then
the generality
connected to the requirements to
understand a specific mind
which I think is the same
um
cognitive associativity between like
Nate that's a whole Marco blanket
LaPlace approximation the Tony mechanics
like that we always talk about so that's
my first take is just like okay well
yeah he may work here or there but
um also Stanford doesn't say that it's
Gordon's law of collective Behavior
but also there's a lot of different
Norms around communication and another
adjacency to kind of explore to based
upon how we're talking about active like
to say the least as at least
instrumental and realist
but also as I again all of you have
brought up in previous discussions like
there's so many other
uh perspectives interpretation
so if a statistical paper came out some
gene expression study from 1992 or some
uh height blood pressure risk related
study
Pearson's progression law
is proven
linear regression explains how
something happens
that's also playing into this kind of
like scientific positivism
again not necessarily the place for the
whole falsificationism of science
disproves doesn't prove
but to to see here's the
um what the science do
how is science related to law
whose ideas are whoms
what acronyms do you already have to
know
an account of a natural process
legitimizing
um or endorsing even applications of
some similar
technical method
in a different setting
a lot of Rich image Meme and and uh
media
fun ahead of us
yeah Andrew throwing memes the LK 99 I
don't even know
but
what if uh someone's like this is a uh
you know room temperature super
cognitive process
actually LK 99 was exactly what I had in
mind
when I talked about
um yeah promising something that can't
be delivered
yeah again there's so much more to say
on this like it's just the complex
consequences of different regimes of
attention
it's so so much more complex and like
good or bad or for whom or over what
time scale
and uh
surfing the 100 foot wave with
popularization and also connecting
people like just to be explicit to come
to the textbook group and to volunteer
be an intern at The Institute
then there's an actionable path from
going from like being enthralled by a
podcast
to working in that tradition
so
it's all happening in the ecosystem
and we're just
seeing how we see it from the
a few of us who are here just in this
slash any given moment
all right Neil which one of your
questions do you think is most relevant
uh
well perhaps perhaps the most
controversial one is the how important
is the theory of free energy
minimization so we could could do that
oh yeah
really this is a question of qualitative
versus quantitative
um
the notion of free energy is very
quantitative
but is it
how essential is it
uh
it's a way of formalizing and Computing
something so so useful from an
engineering perspective
isn't it just enough to say well the
brain is it's uh a load of neurons in
the brains are working in a
a self-organizing
fashion with uh some I want to use
fireman's phrase or ratchet and pool
mechanism to to always be want to be
moving gradually towards a better
solution
um
so then we have this this uh quantity
free energy
um
that's that's incomputable
effectively uh that's that we can say
well that's that's a macroscopic
um quantity but it's it's it doesn't get
used anything in any way
um as
as it does in some machine learning
algorithms
it's uh so you know so it's purely
epiphenomenal it doesn't it doesn't
actually do anything other than well
to help understand
what's going on
um so how how
[Music]
important is yeah
that whole look uh quantitative side of
things to the
to all of the uh the qualitative aspects
of that active inference
so implicit is is my my thought that it
isn't uh
it isn't essential
yeah this is a very interesting question
it's a very JF claudger type point
like how different can it be than
outside in variational Bays
contrasted with
jf's constructed Lego symbolic
implementation
with no no equations no variational
updating so I think that's a really
important area to explore Ali go for it
I will actually
um
looking at active inference framework
um I mean
superficially we can we can see lots of
similarities and even
um I don't know probably some uh
identical uh conceptual components uh
with some other Frameworks such as
predictive processing and uh predictive
coding and so on but
in my opinion the main difference of
active inference uh one of the main
difference of active influence from the
other related Frameworks is exactly what
fep enables active inference to do
namely it puts the optimization of
surprises as the main character of the
whole scenario so you see this is uh the
novel perspective of active inference as
compared to all the other Frameworks
because uh
of course in all the other perspectives
we have the Notions of I don't know
anticipating actions and so on and
basing some decision making to basing
the the decision making on the
prediction and anticipate the
anticipation of actions and also
perception but uh I mean the way fep
reframes this whole scenario and as I
said puts the surprisal optimization uh
to the Forefront as the main character
uh makes it much more elegant on one
hand and on the other uh it makes it
much more broader than all the other
Frameworks because we know that
predictive coding predictive processing
they're mainly restricted to
biological intelligence or biological I
don't know cognition and whatever but uh
we know from uh at least 2019 that the
same mathematical technology can be
applied to a whole range a whole array
of
um ontological entities and uh it's not
fundamentally restricted to uh
biological sentience or intelligence so
this is the key reframing and the key
novel perspective that fep provides to
active imprints and
if if you look at it
um
I mean these kinds of fundamental
reframings uh and uh somehow pivoting
the whole structure of a scientific
theory based on just a single reframing
of a of an essential component is
something that uh that can be witnessed
throughout the whole history of science
time and time again and some of the most
profound insights of
um
that's been gained in throughout the
entire history of modern science uh has
been
they've been gained from this exact
mechanism of changing the perspective uh
based on some redefinition and some
reconceptualization of the established
facts and established theories so in
that sense active inference and its
um underlying fep uh to my opinion can
be seen as I mean it's comparable to all
of these quote-unquote revolutionary
scientific theories uh in that regard
probably thank you
great chapter 10ism
super Super Bowl set
I think this helps differentiate us
again while we're in chapter 10 which is
essentially doing this exact work
wrapping up and connecting
non-technically without figures just
connecting the dots 10.3
it also connects us to the cybernetics
side it's non-contentious that
cybernetic systems can be modeled input
output
it's also non-contentious to do
multi-agent simulation
and then coming from whether just a pure
pragmatic perspective in a finite world
or increasingly from the holographic
approach and the Chris Fields physics is
information processing physics of
boundaries
information processing and
thermodynamics and boundaries also kind
of converging
on a multi-agent thermo informational
input output framework
and when we're talking pedagogically
sometimes it could be like well it's
like input output but you could have
like just an oscillator like just a sine
wave or something like that now also I'm
sure the sine wave can be understood as
doing the path lease action all of this
that is the generality of the framework
and it really does pivot or have a
fulcrum as you described Ali as the
actual censoring of surprisal in
principle
in literally in principle and in fact
slash practice slash deed
detractable
bounded probably approximately correct
bounded rationality
in this situation variational Bayesian
mechanics
but Quantum Hardware software could be
used surely other kinds of computational
implementations can be used but the
censoring of surprisable in principle
with the bounded approximation of
surprisal with all of the work of the
bounded surprisal being bounded
surprisable about a given model
can't talk like generally about the L2
Norm for some cohort of linear
regressions you haven't named yet that's
just not enough information to to say
further
so the theory
takes an essential
normative
Focus
on surprisal minimization and therefore
bridging to the practice with uh
attracted by uh attractable optimizable
bound
so
no contention with other cybernetics
Frameworks they want to explain
observables as a loss function that's
awesome perceptual control theory
RL they want to have structures or
unstructured or fixed or dynamic
cognitive architectures
also all good
um they want to include action
and sense making and use a variational
autoencoder or a variational Bayesian
modeling imperative specifically
that's interesting
Gray Zone question is that implicit fep
if it's literally already providing a
particular partitioned example
that would be very interesting dark fep
literature search
but it's actually those Works which
arguably are used every day in terms of
statistics algorithms
by reframing the scenario it's like hey
we don't have to reduce uncertainty
slash bound uncertainty slash maximize
model evidence on the reward function
turn the surprisal bounding on itself
purely statistically
that doesn't mean it's going to be
perfect because first there's the
information computation bounds Chris
Fields uh Wolfram all of that
and then just practically your
implementation is going to be like
just realistically put together by you
and however you actually put it together
sorry talking about in principle like
exploring blueprints for buildings
discussing very broadly maybe even
usefully over broad possible buildings
in principle without even wondering if
they can be built or anything like that
or are we really in the game talking
about motor disorders in this context of
this situation
very very different Waters
fep and octymph though
it can be uh
assured as far as we believe
that there is a fundamental relationship
that seemingly we learn more about
brings in more pieces because it's a
pretty common
useful as well as
converged upon Forest utility already
enabling a lot of the shorter term work
to be
scholarly
and of course all pending Etc et cetera
Etc
but that's
as Ali has pointed out
as they call it the structure of
scientific revolutions
and so in that way that's an interesting
and provocative uh area to explore
Ollie
um also on a related point and uh
getting back to the previous discussion
we had about the nature of Consciousness
sentence awareness and so on uh so uh
Philip ball has this recent book uh
called The Book of Minds which is a 500
page tone but he recently gave a talk to
the Royal Institution
um it's titled uh let me see yeah it's
what is a mind uh so in this talk he
he concentrate on just one chapter of
this whole book uh namely uh the space
of sorry yeah the space of possible
Minds so more often than not we think of
all of these
uh concepts related to mind such as
intelligence agency sentience and so on
as a kind of one-dimensional spectrum
one-dimensional Continuum but uh Philip
Paul here
shows that uh it would probably be more
um I mean conducive to further uh
development the development of further
future theories if we conceive a kind of
multi-dimensional space of possible
Minds which can have
the access such as agency experience
intelligence and Consciousness and it
it draws a kind of multi-dimensional
space such as this and I was thinking
active inference can actually
provide sufficient tools to Traverse
this whole Space of possible Minds if
one tries to put all of these different
axes
related to one of the key trade-offs
that's been that unfolds through the
central equations of active inference so
basically uh I was thinking that
probably or perhaps the central
equations of active inference can be
used uh as a kind of uh mathematical
tool to Traverse this whole possible uh
by using uh all the all the trade-offs
that we've seen throughout the whole
book uh such as explore exploit
phenomena or other kinds of dilemmas
that we've seen before so yeah I just
wanted to share
and this connection with you because I
believe
there can be some potential
uh interesting connections between these
two theories
that's great another kind of recent uh
connection I was just listening to a
little of this machine learning Street
talk with
Stephen Wolfram and he starts talking
about yes the rouliad and and all the
other work and it's really also
impressive how much he condenses it and
how much they progressed
and then he's like talking about a
physics of the Observer and a framework
for observation and I was just like
that's where they need to kind of like
Direct Time stamps clear ontologically
structured rhetoric
I mean
we're in the farmer's market face still
overall
and how far away is it really from
processing and analyzing
on one on one branch processing the
analyzing speech
to develop appropriate
paths and wayfinding and guiding and all
of that
even if it's Stephen Wolfram giving him
the most informative on-ramps just like
we would for anyone
on the computational side and
also to Neil's Point focus with what's
the qualitative side
and the true cognitive the
phenomenological
side the social side
and I think that's one reason why
um with with
scholarly work like that of Mel Andrews
and and Mal and others
that
integrates discussion around model
building
it also draws upon the pragmatic and the
abductive and the semiotic and a lot of
other
strongly process oriented we talk about
process ontologies
um all these different
features
uh
being woven in at the very least
compatibly
but compatibly which is to say
open-endedly
articulated
in principle
that's
of course we're just having discussions
who knows what's over under confidence
just just saying how it strikes me at
this moment we wouldn't really want a
better imperative based upon what we
understand at least what I personally
understand
something along those lines
that sets the stage for
multi-perspectival
modeling of diverse intelligences
setting that composability it's like if
it doesn't have composability
and the unopinionated
uh kind of nature collab as the
collaborative project
that's what we want collaborative
project
essential project
critical infrastructure
specific project Ryan Smith used a
stomach uh electrode
to test this hypothesis about the vagus
nerve and the role of this like
neuropeptide and this muscle uh pattern
then we're we're in the standard
scientific expanded scientific space
in the process Theory Space chapter six
chapter nine did you look at the whole
system did you consider systematic
factors what what trade-offs did you
make is modeling
is the process and pipeline reproducible
do we have the code like in chapter nine
can you make a figure about the
experiment just like connected to the
figures in the textbook
like reviewer type functions
but as we often bring up reviewers are
not going into whether L2 Norm or L1
Norm was the statistically appropriate
choice
I know in ethology
many times we just said we looked at
this other paper or just this is a
commonly used approach for this
statistical technique
so
putting a lot of weight and focus on the
Last Mile
and the specifics which
is obvious
like Pearson's not brought out every
time somebody does or doesn't use an r
squared to mobilize an arguments or make
a decision
that's so many levels away Einstein is
not brought out except ingest when the
planes are late
so
a lot of a lot of um
morphological and Behavioral
development
but one of the key practices
um a one thing that Wolfram was saying
was like there are certain things about
this or that that have to be the case
like he was talking about our continuous
time perception even though it's the
hypergraph like the discretized
hypergraph at the lower level
uh with that kind of like averages over
all the computations I believe
um something like that
um and then like we're orders magnitude
larger and slower we average out we core
screen talked about that then the theory
of the Observer and he's like yeah there
might be like other things about
communication or about observation or
systems that also like must be the case
so I think there's kind of like in terms
of the anthropic principle slash
anthropic fallacy
um
it's almost like
I believe that we will through chapter
and Beyond like hey how many careers
like this is not just hot takes on a
podcast these are many many careers in
many many directions of many many
academic departments a lot of research
programs startups a lot of funding
Cycles around what is or isn't plausible
AI winter
um all the implications causes and
consequences of cybernetics research
it's like this is the umbrella that
is on the table
connected only to other accounts
so barring things that we learn on a
week by week basis
so at least scale the pragmatic value
to how relevant it is
and then calibrate your epistemic scalar
to
what and how you do and don't know like
we all do and don't know and only speak
from our own experience
we can have a cognitive modeling
analysis
what happens when somebody who is not to
pick on any field or any topic or
anything like that someone who's like oh
I love that citation
or like that's my job
or like I know that really well or my
dissertation was in that what happens
in the moment of contextualization
not to get too meta but again whether
it's artisanal Farmers Market status
and just like well anecdotally people
who are um doing psychiatric work or who
are interested in like for example
chronic pain as like several of our very
committed colleagues are
like they prefer this
that can be approached by kind of
naively or expertly
qualitatively and or quantitatively
so we're in in the end of this
um cohort of uh three of the textbook
group
so what is it really about the textbook
how do we really want to think about its
role in the ecosystem
like impact on people's learning
production of different materials
for different
consumptions and publishings
what any of you think about that
just to give one other random take just
kind of unstructured thinking about it
is like
um
I was thinking of walking down the aisle
at a bookstore and there's different
Frameworks caching or vying for
attention and I know it sounds obvious
that it has to be differentiated
but pointing out that there's
differentiation
on multiple axes
as a consequence
of
it sounds wild or weird or however you
want to see it at first but the
minimization of surprise has a central
phenomena
and that
simple starting positionality or stance
along with some other core memes that I
think needs to be worked out and
understood the relationship to like
embody and all this other stuff
that rolls downhill differently
helps you rethink differently see a lot
of phenomena
maybe theoretical transdisciplinary
synthesis is not your
um trajectory in life that's totally
chill
obvious it doesn't need to be said but
just to be clear that this is in that
the just the the where and the when and
the how and The Who
in relationship to
if the
um actual
which we saw
uh at least the the movie poster for
earlier in our discussion
uh and also one of the points is uh
um you see given the rapid development
of active inference literature since the
publication of this book uh I believe
um it might not be a terribly bad idea
if uh beginning from the next cohort uh
we somehow begin to incorporate more uh
actively some of the uh findings of
recent literature into the discussions
because
um I mean with this pace of development
that active inference is experiencing
right now uh it might sound a bit
grandiose but I think it's not unlike uh
the situation that quantum physics
experienced uh in the early 20th century
so uh as we know from the history of
quantum physics uh almost every year and
even
every few months radically new uh
understanding of quantum theory uh
appeared which fundamentally shaped what
we know as quantum physics and I believe
active imprints kind of
uh taking a similar trajectory because
with
of course not all of the
um papers that's been published since
the publication of this book but some of
the uh groundbreaking papers that really
shifted our understanding of what active
inference is all about and uh somehow
refined uh the more vague Concepts that
we still see in this book and try to
make them more precise and
make it more coherent with the rest of
the theory so uh yeah as I said in my
opinion it might not be a bad idea to
look at some of these
developments from the next beginning
from the next cohort
thanks a lot Ali Neil
yeah
and grows with any new area it grows it
gets beyond the point where where any
individual can keep track of things
um
I was wondering I mean maybe the active
inference Institute is
effectively doing this already but I'm
just imagining if if there was an annual
report let's say The Institute uh
produced an annual report
providing an overview of of what
happened uh
the significant developments uh in in
the last year
um
so that you were talking earlier about
you know there's so many different ways
in that it touches on
uh that people might
um
well have some involvement to do with
active inference but then you know this
this tiny area
uh how do you get them to have some
bigger perspective whether there's
education such as this book
but how do you enable them to carry on
um
maintaining that because because they
can't be reading thousands of Journal
papers or a year
just on the active inference when
that might actually only be a relatively
small part of their
their wider research
and
whereas The Institute should be able to
provide some
oath
is it it's not I'm not just thinking
that a review of um something so said
this and so said that but some
sort of bigger perspective on on where
on what's Happening so like a whole load
of new art new Publications were in
in this direction say social sciences
and
and that to to help people
thanks these are such good comments I
really agree Ali and I and now actually
kind of like pseudo-templated
a little bit like a research Roundup
so it's a seed project that's just one
possible mechanism not to not jump to a
solution or anything like that but like
I also totally agree like yeah we fixed
some Errata and typos we aggregated some
people's input
that's that's local refinement and it's
it's adding value and so on but then
okay now Jonathan and Ali have PDFs on
this equation and that equation
that's like and then you have
sanjeev's work as all of you no
and uh
The annotation work is infinite and I
think we've in some ways laid out what
certain paths look like like for example
using the ontology seriously annotating
equations with the verbal descriptions
getting all the figures boxes tables
eventually even paragraphs into tabular
form
like we have the massively collaborative
possibilities and that's not to say
they're even being underused at all
by human and or non-human agents
it's just part of a co-creation
so it's not about just like
um just like single dimensional
perspectives on Consciousness or
anything like that
are limited if if not worse
um multiple projects should speak to the
bigger perspective
I think there's the important
observational role like here's how
surprise was used in this paper at this
time
I associate that with the kind of trust
finder architecture like rhetorical
assertion not to get too technical but
different expressions are made in the
ecosystem
ingressed and or intentionally
and
we have different strategies and
approaches and and projects
that are anticipatory and maintenance
oriented and historical
to improve our sense making
there are some interns who are doing
such
amazing work and that's only the
fraction some fraction of people
um who are not just in their own way and
in their own game which is everyone
so like what we're what we can really do
I'm happy to have these fundamental
conversations
I I just I we're not going to be able to
enumerate or evaluate or anything like
that but
par some you know keeping the par flame
alive
maybe with a discussion changing the
time Ollie and I will have completed our
background videos
and then we can kind of assess like
here's the rules
um
here's the first versions of the
background materials
go through it
at these you know small groups so there
could be a lot of decentralized ways to
continue that or at least just low
preparation ways for different
facilitators
and then
maybe we need cohorts who have Chris
fields
um maybe we need a special integration
units and projects like that just having
a reading group follow AVL in social
sciences and follow Chris in in the
you're going to be intersecting and and
uh engaging and still on the fractal
wave
and we're always going to be only using
the systems that we have
can't be waiting for Future tools but we
will use them as they arrive
and just supporting the sustainability
of that for the ecosystem is our
Focus
yeah
another thought just as we're in kind of
last minutes of 10. so it's like all
this theoretical scope yeah it could
just be another
um node in the same space but the claim
is kind of like it generalizes a lot of
them relates a lot of them formally
um maybe even envelops all of them
um
at least socio socio-technically if not
even way way way deeper and broader and
and everything like that so it's like
however much Theory scope you think this
covers maybe you're super familiar with
literature you're for every single
citation you're like oh yeah you know
exactly why it's there then
this argument is poised to your
adjacency
because this is the perspective of the
authors or if you're not super familiar
with these areas it may be sufficient
just to understand them as being like
broad topics of Interest
if not addressing importance systems in
the real world but when we really think
about these as being the major threads
of accounts and statistics for cognitive
behavioral systems
it's not like there's some other like
secret 11th Theory to just being like
censored in the citation literature I
mean I'd leave it to a meta-analysis to
say more but but nobody reads this and
says wow you're you're ignoring like
this entire massive thing yeah maybe go
into more detail on adaptive resonance
Theory or go into more detail on this on
one given area
but when the broad threads are
represented
and the arguments are made formally in
text based upon an implicit first
principle
the scope and the relevance of the
learning has to be this theoretical
scope and the consequences on systems of
Interest
doesn't mean it has to be overwhelming
in the moment but people bring up real
things in the textbook group and it is
about real things because education is
about real things
I would like to hear any of your all's
thoughts on chapter 10 now as we close
cohort three
don't worry authors will get the final
word not us
any thoughts
foreign
so many great comments and I know it's
only the tip of the iceberg of what was
like said
or maybe it was never even said and then
of course what said it's only the
iceberg with with what is thought
but it's so funny it was right back
there
with the sentience
with the 11th round of the sentience
debate
and it's like
is it over promising
but it's a it's a different system of
interest it's not the same thing as
learning like
learning epistemic value that's why it's
sometimes fun just to learn about things
for their epistemic value
there's parts that we know has pragmatic
value
there's parts that we know have
epistemic value
what other imperative
are you acting and inferring under
and then one route that Ali highlighted
very
um particularly earlier was the central
character main character energy for
surprisal
and it kind of
uh close in that Nexus
is the qualitative
but but formal
potentially qualitative compositional
about existence
existentials
and that ties it to homeostasis and all
of that
ties it to observation and all of that
it opens up another degree of freedom
the Axel constants
Mobius strip
it's not about it's about how you got
there
like this describes systems with
persistence
do you have a better descriptor
but that doesn't mean that constructing
it is a guarantee of future persistence
you know past returns does not guarantee
future returns
or whatever they say there
but
you may be able to say certain things
but the existentialism is a natural fit
in information landscapes
because it kind of blurs it doesn't
actually blur but it can but it
conceptually integrates the measurement
and the existential
Anaconda common footing
super General analytical representations
the exact same kind from like
variational physics and mechanics
information Theory
Quantum category Theory
Dynamic systems
all their notation special case
all the math that people are using to
describe systems of Interest
compositionality
recognition of new
underlying special case phenomena
just as Buckminster Fuller always
pointed to
recognition of special case phenomena
upon generalization
also related to the revolution model
that Ali mentioned
and that is the thing
if you just have a particular partition
but then
you have them fitting an L2 Norm
which is not unlike what a structural
equation model is actually in structural
equation modeling is used in SPM and I'm
sure there's all kinds of different
variants and stuff but it's like that's
like a kind of massively linear
parametric
can include time series just like all
the sarima methods and all of that so a
lot of the same ability to describe like
changing causal relationships
little-known fact existed in SPM
so a lot of the practice
in principle
was totally totally addressed by SPM
textbook
various modules became increasingly
recognized
centrality of action the pragmatic turn
in Neuroscience all that
those uh recognitions uh were either
articulations that were not understood
to have already existed
like the idea that you could just extend
uh
the kind of Coleman filter like
predictive processing algorithm arising
in video compression
and then just like pop action in
and get active inference
with all of these even immediately
apparent philosophical implications for
people who are studying those topics
and the maintenance of the key feature
with the physics-based first principles
singular imperative
so recognitions of articulations that
that um
suggested
also profitable and fruitful directions
importance critiques and and
re-understandings
and developments
uh not just related to notation for
example generative model and generative
process which as we've discussed more
recently is not the way that it's often
being discussed so does that lead to an
entire secondary discussion or do we
just continue forward mostly with such
and such
but the particular partition
and the over the last years
the refinement of so many different
aspects such that we're basically
like preparing to scramble
not really
how to even synthesize
hence the ultra descriptive
deflationary ontology
at assertion based architecture that we
hope is going to bring in a lot of
diverse ways of knowing and remodeling
and sense making
and
there will be a lot of difference
angles and overlaps
like what if there's a statistics
Professor who's just feels a certain way
about this
how does that situate them in
relationship to the theoretical
apparatus as understood by any other
given person or by any other group of
other people
so how to really retain the
[Music]
um
singular Focus
amidst all the specifics
it's comforting to expect and prefer
that we have the framework that is on
the path towards that
composability extensibility etc etc all
the phenomena that we discuss
and what's the other
aspect to it
and the textbook's not life
so how to emphasize that too
and really integrate it in people's
living and learning
make it
what it can be
so we could definitely think a lot and
no specific dates for
cohorts are set
but maybe you know who knows social
sciences cohort 2
Chris Fields cohort II
par
it's people's
attention slash nestmate level
contributions that actually embody those
things
and so after the acclimation of like the
kind of whoa
there's still so much work and that will
continue to be
so
it's been a total honor to Neil Ali and
esmail and everybody else who
contributed to totally to this cohort
um any any last comments on cohort 3.
fascinating Journey as always
I mean the summary well summary chapter
will always do that and sort of throwing
everything there is in front of you but
yeah there is so much to the whole
to the subject isn't there I've brought
in from so many different places
it really is
foreign
yeah we've all
learned a lot it's been a very great end
so I guess next week the the day of the
symposium
I mean
we can discuss more but we'll see
what we may want to do or how we want to
proceed in the coming
um cohorts so thanks again
see y'all next time
bye thanks everyone thanks bye thanks